<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of interest or usury as to the common practice, stated and examined in a private letter to a person of quality who desired satisfaction in that point / by T.S.</title>
            <author>T. S. (Thomas Seymour)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16412898</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16412898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105386</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105386)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1158:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of interest or usury as to the common practice, stated and examined in a private letter to a person of quality who desired satisfaction in that point / by T.S.</title>
                  <author>T. S. (Thomas Seymour)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Guy ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Usury --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105386:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105386:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The CASE of INTEREST OR, USURY: As to the Common Practice, Stated and Examined; In a Private Letter to a Perſon of Quality, who deſired Satisfaction in that Point.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non ſequeris Turbam ad facïendum malum:</hi> Thou ſhalt not follow the Multitude to do Evil,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vide Profectum! In Principo Legis a</hi> Fratribus <hi>tantum Faenus tollitur; in Propheta, ab</hi> Omnibus <hi>Fanus removetur. Porro ſub Evangelio</hi> Virtutis Augmentum <hi>eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S.</hi> Hieronymus <hi>in cap.</hi> 18. Ezechielis.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Behold the Progreſs! In the Beginning of the Law, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> was only forbidden among <hi>Brethren.</hi> Under the Prophets, it was prohibited among <hi>All.</hi> But in the times of the Goſpel there is a greater <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>S. <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Comment. on the 18th. of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Guy,</hi> at the Corner Shop of Little <hi>Lumbard-Street</hi> and <hi>Corne-Hill,</hi> near <hi>Wool-Church</hi> Market. 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105386:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105386:2"/>
            <head>To the Fair Pattern of Piety, Vertue, and Nobleneſs, Mrs. <hi>A. M.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHat was lately <hi>compoſed</hi> at your <hi>Commands,</hi> is now in your name <hi>Expoſed</hi> to the <hi>World;</hi> with this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Advantage, that where my <hi>Reaſons</hi> flagg, or are deficient, the moſt attractive Motive of your <hi>Example</hi> will undoubtedly prevail.</p>
            <p>For if Divine Plato dogmatiz'd right, <hi>Vertue in her ſelf hath ſuch powerful Charmes, that ſhould ſhe but aſſume a viſible ſhape, all would immediately become her Inamourato's.</hi> And therefore I queſtion not, but it will have great <hi>Influence</hi> on the <hi>Reader,</hi> when he ſhall underſtand of a <hi>Young Lady,</hi> whoſe firſt Demand at the Entrance on her Eſtate, was, how ſhe might Regulate it according to the ſevereſt Principles of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>The Pious Weeper of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his Lamentations, <hi>chap. 3.27.</hi> acquaints us that <hi>it is good for a Man to bear the Yoak from his Youth,</hi> Quia levavit ſe ſuper ſe, <hi>He hath lifted himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove himſelf.</hi> Madam, by this <hi>Early</hi> and <hi>Heroick Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> you have not only exceeded and anticipated the General Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of thoſe who knew you, but gain'd a moſt compleat Victory over your ſelf, which in the Eſtimate of a Wiſe Man, is more than <hi>Alexander</hi> did in Conquering the World. You have new taught Man-kinde that forgotten Leſſon of King <hi>Solomon; To honour God with our Subſtance,</hi> Prov. <hi>3.9.</hi> and that our
<pb facs="tcp:105386:3"/>
               <hi>Real Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Lawful Uſury,</hi> is, <hi>faenerari Domino, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo pauperis,</hi> By pittying the Poor, to Lend to the Lord, <hi>chap. 19.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qui dedit Velle, donet &amp; Perficere.</hi> May indulgent Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who hath begun a Good Work in your Soul, perfect it, and daily water that <hi>Blooming Goodneſs</hi> his own Right Hand hath planted; till laden with the fruit of Good Works, you wax <hi>Ripe</hi> for Heaven, to be tranſplanted to the Paradiſe of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe this Addreſs by way, both of Encouragement, and Congratulation, in the Words of King <hi>Laemuel</hi>'s Mother's advice, <hi>Prov. 31.29.30. Multae Filiae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Many Daughters have gathered Riches together; but thou haſt ſurpaſſed them all: Comlineſs is Deceitful, and Beauty is Vain; the Woman that feareth our Lord, ſhall be praiſed,</hi> which is ſufficient to wipe off the ſuſpicion of flattery in</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Madam,</hi> 
               </salute> 
               <signed>Your true Honourer, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted Servant. <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>3d. 1673.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105386:3"/>
            <head>The CASE of INTEREST OR USURY: As to the Common Practice, Stated and Examined in a Private Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot but with Infinite ſatisfaction comply with your Vertuous deſires lately intimated to me by your Unckle; and likewiſe highly applaud your Generous Reſolutions, in not attempting any Method for the Increaſe of that plentiful Eſtate, which Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs hath-caved out to you, as to the Concernes of this; World, till you have a ſufficient Warrant to Juſtifie the Way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</p>
            <p>For you muſt know, there is ſuch a thing as <hi>God's Bleſſing,</hi> which is of maine Importance, both for the <hi>Procuring, Preſerving,</hi> and <hi>Improving</hi> in Eſtate. Without this (which moſt aſſuredly is never entayled on Goods, either Unlawfully <hi>Got</hi> or <hi>Manag'd</hi>) all <hi>Humane Providence, Induſtry</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> are altogether <hi>Inſignificant;</hi> and inſtead of <hi>Raiſing</hi> we ſhall but <hi>Raze,</hi> and Deſtroy both our Names and Family; and which, is far more Conſiderable, our own pretious Souls.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105386:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Proverbs, <hi>chap.</hi> 13.11. informs us that <hi>Wealth haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> (or as the gloſs expounds it, When we make ſpeed to be Rich by any means whatever, either Direct or Indirect) <hi>ſhall be diminiſhed,</hi> which is no more than what his Father <hi>David</hi> told us before, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1, 2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the Lord build the Houſe, they have labour'd in vain that build it. It is vain for you to riſe before Light,</hi> &amp;c. Or, if for a final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of this matter, you require a more abſolute Authority, behold a greater than either <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Solomon;</hi> God himſelf, who thus by his Prophet <hi>Aggeus,</hi> c. 1.5, 6. makes a ſolemne Proclamation: <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoaſts; Conſider your ways; you have ſown much, and have brought in little: You have eaten, and have not been filled: You have covered your ſelves, and have not been warmed; and he that gathered Wages, put them into a broken bag. You have looked for more, and behold it became leſs; you brought it into the Houſe, and I puffed at it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From which, with a multitude of other Paſſages in Holy Writt, theſe two remarkable Concluſions may undeniably be Collected. 1. That many taking a prepoſterous way, and unlawful courſes, to better that Condition Wiſe Providence hath caſt them into, pull down a Curſe upon the whole, inſtead of increaſing a part; and are ſo far from Thriving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their expectation and moral Probabilities, that by the juſt Judgment of God, ſome accident or other hath, like a ſecret Moth and Canker, eaten out what ever their care and pains had hoarded together. Daily Experience teſtifying, that as the Debauch'd, Intemperate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, frequently tranſmits his bodily Diſeaſes to his Children; ſo the fraudulent oppreſſing devices of Unconſionable men, convey down an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Plague on their Poſſeſſions; which, either by an inſenſible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection waſtes and conſumes them, or gnaws out the heart and comfort of them; which Content and Comfort conſiſts in that which our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion teaches us, in acquieſcing with that moderate, competent fortune the All-Wiſe Goodneſs hath allotted to our ſhare: So that the ſhorteſt way to be Rich, as one hath well obſerved, is not an over-eager enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Eſtates through the ordinary ſlights and Leger-demains of Earthly-minded men; but by contracting our deſires to the diſpoſal of Providence and our own proper Care and Induſtry, without incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Labour, Sweat, and Hazard of our Neighbour, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of doing him a Courteſie in <hi>Lending,</hi> but in reallity Ruining both him and his by a moſt Tyrannical Exaction of <hi>more</hi> than was delivered into his Hands.</p>
            <p>The other Corollary we may deduce, is, that not only unjuſt ſhifts ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105386:4"/>in obtaining at firſt, or afterwards in bettering our External Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; but even a neglect to make that good uſe of Temporal Bleſſings, which our Heavenly Father intended when he beſtowed them on us, (much more the abuſe of them, to the gratifying our ſenſual Pleaſures, Luſts and Vanities) is both accountable for, at that great and terrible laſt Aſſizes, when a ſtrict Examen ſhall be made of every Idle Word, (unleſs we think our Saviour was in jeſt when he ſo poſitively declared <hi>Math.</hi> 12.37. <hi>I ſay unto you, that every Idle Word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall render an Account for it in the Day of Judgment.</hi> What then ſhall we think of thoſe prodigious expences which Pride and Luxury have ſquander'd away?) and frequently, either ſooner or later, even in this World derives ſome ſignal Vengeance on the Offendors, either in their perſons, or, which is equivalent, their near Poſterity; God himſelf having Avow'd no leſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. <hi>I am the Lord thy God, Mighty, Jealous, Viſiting the Iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children, unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hate me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For, whatever we may conceit of our ſelves, we are not abſolute Lords and Maſters of what we enjoy here, but only Stewards, intruſted with ſo many Talents as the Supreme Wiſdome judges requiſite for our Capacity, (ſome in a larger, ſome in a more ſlender meaſure;) and therefore we are obliged, both to be contented with the Portion aſſign'd us, and neither <hi>improve</hi> nor <hi>employ</hi> it otherwiſe than the known Will of the <hi>Beſtower</hi> will authorize us. Otherwiſe it is to be feared, we ſhall too truly experience what S. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great hath forewarned us of; That <hi>the exact Reckoning which the Divine Tribunal will infallibly one day make with us, increaſes and multiplies not only in proportion to the good things we receive, but alſo to the tricks and ſhifts uſed to advance them:</hi> Or what our Bleſſed Saviour teaches in the Goſpel, <hi>That it is as uſy for a Camel to paſs through the eye of a Needle, as for a Rich man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> Which is no ſuch Paradox, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what the Apoſtle hath obſerved, that <hi>The Love of Money is the Root of all Evil;</hi> and the maniſold temptations Wealth betrays a man to, both in <hi>Getting, Keeping, Imploying,</hi> and <hi>Leaving</hi> it, as would be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to inſtance in moſt of the Villanies committed in all ages of the World, upon this very ſcore.</p>
            <p>But it is not my purpoſe, (neither I preſume, your deſire) to unrip all thoſe <hi>Intrigues</hi> and <hi>Myſteries of Iniquity</hi> wherewith the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds at this day, as to the point of <hi>Thriving</hi> and <hi>Improvement.</hi> My deſign in this Preface was only to let you ſee, that it is good <hi>Policy</hi> as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105386:5"/>well as <hi>Piety</hi> to avoyd thoſe <hi>By-Paths,</hi> and <hi>Stratagems</hi> wholly unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, which in the concluſion will be found to be the fatal <hi>Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> rather than <hi>Augmentation</hi> of an Eſtate.</p>
            <p>To omit therefore thoſe more open crimes of <hi>Cheating, Oppreſſion, Sacriledge,</hi> or detaining from God what was once Conſecrated to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall only freely diſcover the Truth at preſent, concerning that <hi>Epidemical Raging</hi> and <hi>Reigning Diſeaſe</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> yet ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally look'd on as otherwiſe, that it is become in a manner a Jack of all Trades, an Univerſal Profeſſion; and though the moſt ſordid and mechanical in it ſelf (aſhamed even of its own name, witneſs the dwind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> into <hi>Intereſt</hi>) yet practiſed by the greateſt Pretenders to Gentility (however <hi>under-board</hi> as much as poſſible, out of ſight (a ſhrewd Argument, all is not juſtifiable.) And I ſhall not ſpeak of it in it's <hi>Latitude,</hi> or at <hi>large,</hi> but only as it is limited by the <hi>Laws of the Land.</hi> For of it ſelf, it is ſuch a ſpreading Leproſie, that it was high time for the civil Phyſitian (I mean the Magiſtrate) to lend a helping hand, and hinder the growth, where he could not wholly prevent the Infection, barely <hi>permitting</hi> what he could not without a far greater Inconven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>prohibit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Queſtion</hi> in debate (if there may any <hi>Queſtion</hi> be made of a thing ſo poſitively decided by all <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi>) may without any farther <hi>Preamble,</hi> be thus fairly ſtated as to us here in <hi>England,</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whether <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Uſe,</hi> though permitted by the Laws of the Land, is abſolutely or in it ſelf Lawful, as being Warrantable by the Law of God and Principles of Right Reaſon?</head>
               <p>NOw, <hi>Madam,</hi> though I intend chiefly <hi>your ſatisfaction</hi> in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and conſequently this Diſcourſe is penn'd for your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate peruſal only; yet becauſe it may poſſibly contrary to my intention, happen into their hands who will take the liberty to examine the grounds of this Aſſertion, I muſt crave leave to proceed ſomewhat after the manner of the Schools: However I hope with ſo much <hi>candour</hi> and <hi>perſpicuity,</hi> as may no ways prejudice its main deſign; which, as I premiſed, was ſolely the <hi>removal</hi> of your difficulties. And to teſtifie my own fidelity, and unbiaſſedneſs in the preſent Controverſie, when ever I have occaſion to quote Authorities, either Sacred or Prophane, I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105386:5"/>ſhall readily put my ſelf to the double pains, both of <hi>Tranſcribing,</hi> and <hi>Tranſlating,</hi> that ſo impartial Judges may be better cenſure.</p>
               <p>To begin then with the <hi>Quid Nominis &amp; Rei,</hi> or what it is we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt Uſury (in Latine <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura,</hi> in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) or as we now adayes mince the matter, Intereſt is, <hi>Quidcunque ſolutioni Rei Mutuatae accedit, ipſius Rei <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus gratia, pactione interpoſita, vel hac Intentione habita, in contractu, vel exactione habita poſt contractum,</hi> as the Summu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts uſually define it: That is to ſay, what ever is more than the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the thing Lent, upon the account of the Uſe of the thing, either by vertue of a Contract or Bargain interpoſed, or only with this <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the Bargain (namely, of receiving <hi>More</hi> than was <hi>Lent</hi>) or laſtly by reaſon of ſome action occurring after the Bargain.</p>
               <p>This Deſcription is very exact, and includes all, or moſt of the kindes of Uſury. But being ſomething obſcure to thoſe who are not verſed in <hi>Schoo-Learning,</hi> I ſhall rather give you this following Character of it out of the Angelical Doctor of the Church S. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> 2.2. q. 78. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt quicquid ſupra ſortem accedit:</hi> What ever ſurmounts the Principal is Uſury. Or, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt Pretium pecuniae mutuatae, vel cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſcunque Rei, cujus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus eſt Conſumptio vel Diſtractio ejus.</hi> Uſury is Gaine Received by lending of Money, or any other thing, the Uſe whereof conſiſts in its Conſuming or Alienation.</p>
               <p>Where by the way is to be Noted, that through the barrenneſs of our Engliſh Language, we are forced to uſe the word (Lend) in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Uſury, though it be very improper: For <hi>Mutuum</hi> or <hi>Mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in Latine, which we render by <hi>Lending</hi> in Engliſh, is, <hi>facere de Meo Tuum,</hi> or a Contract, in which the Dominion or Right to any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Number, Weight, or Meaſure, is tranſlated from the <hi>Lender</hi> to the <hi>Borrower (a Mutuante in Mutuarium)</hi> with Obligation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore either the ſame, or the like in kinde and goodneſs. And this for the moſt part happens in things Conſumptible by their very Uſe, as Corne, Wine, Oyle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> among which, Money may be reckoned; for though it be not conſumed, nor periſh in it ſelf, yet it paſſes away from him who trades with it: Whereas in <hi>Lending,</hi> ſtrictly ſpeaking, we give away no <hi>Right</hi> nor <hi>Dominion,</hi> but only the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> for a time. As for example, when I lend my Horſe for a Journey, or my Cloak upon any other occaſion, I grant the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> but not the <hi>Thing.</hi> Whereas in Lending Money, the Borrower is abſolute Maſter, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of it as he pleaſes, when he hath it. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Pawning</hi> and <hi>Hiring</hi> proportionably, this I thought good to intimate,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105386:6"/>for the better underſtanding of the ſubſequent Reaſons in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>In brief then, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is Gain, or Profit bargain'd for, by reaſon of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Lent;</hi> Or, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is what ever is Received beſides the Principal.</hi> The Council of <hi>Agatha</hi> defines it, <hi>Quando amplius requiritur quam da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> when more is demanded than was Lent, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the 36 Pſalm is very clear, <hi>Si faenerareris hominem,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſi mutuo dederis pecuniam tuam, a quo plus quam dediſti expectes; non pecuniam ſolum, ſed aliquid plus quam dediſti, ſive illud triticum ſit, ſive vinum, ſive olcum, ſive quod libet aliud, ſi plus quam dediſti, expectes accipere, faene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores,</hi> &amp;c. If, ſayes that moſt learned and holy Father, thou lendeſt thy Money to any one, from whom thou expecteſt more than thou dideſt Lend; not only Money, but any thing more than thou lendeſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Corne, Wine, or Oyle, or any thing elſe, if thou expecteſt more than thou gaveſt, thou art a Uſurer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor is St. <hi>Jerom</hi> leſs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory in his Commentary on the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel; Putant quidam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuras tantum eſſe in pecunia; quod praevidens ſacra ſcriptura, omnis Rei aufert ſuperabundantiam, ut plus non recipias quam dediſti,</hi>  Some think that Uſury conſiſts only in Money, which the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture foreſeeing, takes away the overplus of every thing, forbidding to Receive <hi>more</hi> than we gave or lent.— What the Holy Scripture determines, we ſhall more fully diſcover by and by.— But Divine St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his firſt book concerning <hi>David,</hi> hath ſo reſolutely ended this Queſtion, that I know not what reply it can admit of; <hi>Item Eſca <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt, &amp; veſtis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt, &amp; Quodcunque accedit ſorti, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt; &amp;, quod velis, ei, nomen imponas, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt;</hi> Uſury, fayes he, may be committed in things eatable; Uſury may be in Garments, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is over and above the Principal, is Uſury, and guild it over with what name you will, it is Uſury.— It is worth our Obſervation (to name it only by the By) how ſhamefac'd and modeſt the Antient Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were in compariſon of our Modern Exactors; they only exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome gratuity (I ſpeak of the honeſt ſort) or Conſideration for the Courteſie, and that uſually in another kinde; a preſent of Corne, Oyle, Wine, or Cloath, or the like, (not 6.10. or 12. <hi>per cent</hi>) and yet how ſharply they are taxed by the Primitive Fathers, and brought within the circle of all thoſe Curſes thundred out againſt the moſt Rigorous and Exacting Uſury.</p>
               <p>But if nothing but Gods own Voyce will ſatisfie in this point, we have it as expreſs as is poſſible, <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 18.8. where delineating forth a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105386:6"/>Righteous Man, he deſcribes him to be one, <hi>Qui ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram non Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modaverit, &amp; Amplius non acceperit;</hi> who hath not Lent to Uſury, and hath not taken <hi>more,</hi> to wit, than the main ſum. So that receiving <hi>more,</hi> and Lending to Uſury, in Gods account, are the very ſelf ſame thing. From the mouths of ſo many Witneſſes it cannot but be evident what Uſury is. And indeed this is the Concepit which all men frame Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of it.</p>
               <p>The notion of the Thing, being thus eſtabliſhed, that we might not <hi>Aerem Verberare,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> phraſes it, combate with the Winde, or argue againſt what no man owns; it remains, that we deliver our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents as to the Problem propoſed, which muſt be in the Negative, namely, that</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> or <hi>Intereſt,</hi> though permitted (or rather limited) by the Laws of this Kingdom and others, is yet abſolutely unlawful, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned by the Law of God, and Principles of Right Reaſon.</head>
               <p>AS to the <hi>Law of God,</hi> the caſe is ſo clear, that I ſcarce know any thing more evidently or frequently, both forbid and threaten'd. And this Topick being of weightieſt moment with thoſe, who ſet the fear of God before their eyes, and have not their <hi>Conſciences ſeared,</hi> as it were <hi>with a hot iron</hi> (<hi>Authorized</hi> to borrow the Apoſtles manner of expreſſion) that is to ſay, altogether ſenſeleſs, hardened, ſtupid, and mortified, and the principles of Religion, Grace, and Good Nature, deſperately extinct through continual Cuſtome, ſenſuality and practice of ſin; I ſhall be the more punctual in preſſing thoſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that may be drawn from <hi>Divine Prohibition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I begin with <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Si pecuniam mutuam dederis populo meo pauperi, qui habitat tecum, non urgebis eum quaſi exactor, nec uſuris op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primes.</hi>— If thou lend Money to my people, being Poor, who dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with thee, thou ſhalt not urge them as an Exactor, nor oppreſs them with Uſuries.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant, that Covetous Wits, and the profeſs'd Patrons of Uſury, have ſound out a double reply to this place. 1. That all Uſury is not here condemned, but only <hi>Exaction, Exceſs, Tyrannical proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and, in a word, only that Uſury which either <hi>ruines,</hi> or very much <hi>Oppreſſes</hi> the borrowing party. This conceipt is ſeconded by the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of <hi>Neſhec</hi> (the Hebrew word for Uſury) which comes from a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105386:7"/>Root importing to <hi>Pinch, Bite, Eat out,</hi> &amp;c. So that petty Intereſt and ſmaller Conſiderations fall not within the compaſs of <hi>Non <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgchis</hi> in the Text, <hi>Thou ſhalt not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rge them.</hi> 2. Another Evaſion is diſcovered in thoſe words, <hi>If thou lend Money to my People, being Poor.</hi> From whence our <hi>Money-mongers</hi> argue, provided they trade only with <hi>Dives,</hi> thoſe <hi>Golden Lads,</hi> whoſe backs are able to bear it, and not with poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the needy <hi>Handycraft-man,</hi> or <hi>Labouring, Peaſant, Salva Res eſt,</hi> they are ſafe enough and <hi>ſhot-proof</hi> againſt the <hi>Cannon-Law</hi> of <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. Their <hi>Banks</hi> may fructifie by an inundation from the <hi>Ocean,</hi> ſo they derive no advantage from the ſhallower <hi>Brooks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this <hi>Varniſh</hi> is ſoon waſhed off. For, 1. Beſides the fallacy that is too often couch'd in the <hi>Etimology,</hi> or <hi>Critical ſcanning</hi> of a word, the ſmall force it hath in cloſe Argumentation, and the great hazard of embroyling moſt of our Fundamentals in a <hi>Logomachie</hi> or Conteſt about words, ſhould theſe <hi>Reparties</hi> to ſo manifeſt Prohibitions be admitted: It is replyed that all Uſury is <hi>Exactive, Corroding</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſive,</hi> (though not equally, <hi>viz.</hi> 6. as much as 10. <hi>per cent.</hi>) Yet more or leſs, it incroaches on my Neighbours Right, and ſecretly gnaws the very bowels of his Eſtate. Not to mention its <hi>Repugnancy</hi> to <hi>Evangelical Charity,</hi> which regards not ſo much whether it notably <hi>incommodates,</hi> or <hi>diſables,</hi> as whether it <hi>aſſiſts</hi> and <hi>advances</hi> the Good and Profit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though our Enemies. As alſo that ſuch an Interpretation thwarts the whole current of Expoſitors. The <hi>Chaldee,</hi> derives it from a word ſignifying <hi>Increaſe,</hi> not <hi>Exaction.</hi> The <hi>Arabick</hi> intimates whatever is <hi>above</hi> the Main or Principal. The <hi>Septuagint,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> the two St. <hi>Gre-Cories, Nyſſen</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen</hi> term it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which Cardinal <hi>Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> a Natural <hi>Grecian</hi> and Scholiaſt upon St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> renders, <hi>Cum dat quis quidpiam, ut plus quam, dederit accipiat:</hi> When one lends ſomething, that he may receive <hi>more, Tertullian</hi> in his fourth book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Marcian,</hi> calls it <hi>Redundantiam Faenoris</hi> the <hi>Redundance</hi> or <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus</hi> of Uſury. St. <hi>Jerom, Amplius</hi> or <hi>More,</hi> whom <hi>Vatablus</hi> follows. <hi>Pagninus</hi> and the reſt term it <hi>Incrementum,</hi> what ever <hi>Increaſes.</hi> And thus Three in the Hundred being <hi>more</hi> than was lent, and eating into the Borrowers Concerns, falls under the charge of <hi>Amplius,</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <hi>more,</hi> and of <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> as well, though not ſo much as Ten; the Theft of five ſhillings being as peremptorily Condemned by, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Steal,</hi> as of 500 pounds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to the buſineſs of the <hi>Poverty</hi> of the Borrower, this Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance no wayes Extuenates the malice of Uſury. For the <hi>Poor</hi> are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105386:7"/>here ſpecified, that a more tender reſpect might be had to their Indigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, as if the Text had run thus, <hi>Thou ſhalt not urge any of thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, nor oppreſs them with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury; but more ſignally beware of Oppreſſing the Poor.</hi> The other is bad enough, but this will prove a <hi>Crying Sin,</hi> and draw down a ſuddain Vengeance. And that here is no force offered to the words, it is obſervable, that excepting this of <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. &amp; <hi>Levit.</hi> 25. in all other places of holy Scripture, there is not the leaſt notice ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>Poor,</hi> but Uſury it ſelf, or taking of <hi>more,</hi> is abſolutely inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to be uſed to the one as well as the other. And as for <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35. I wiſh it were a little better minded. <hi>Si attenuatus fuerit frater tuus,</hi> &amp;c. If thy Brother be impoveriſh'd, and weak of hand, and thou receive him as a Stranger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> take not Uſury of him, nor <hi>more</hi> than thou gaveſt; fear thy God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thou ſhalt not give him thy Money to Uſury, and an Overplus of the fruits thou ſhalt not Exact of him.— Where we have it moſt evidently aſſerted, that to take Uſury, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to receive <hi>More</hi> than we gave; and that both are as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden, as the fear of God is Commanded; and withal it is more than hinted to us, that where the true fear of God is, thoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs will never be practiſed.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, the <hi>Poor</hi> are here Nominated, becauſe they are more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently compelled to Borrow, and conſequently undergo the burden of Uſury, than the <hi>Rich.</hi> Though for my own part, I ſee not but that the <hi>Rich</hi> may be comprehended in the number of the <hi>Poor.</hi> For when a man otherwiſe of a ſufficient Fortune, is reduced to terms of having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to his Neighbour, for that time he may properly be called <hi>Poor,</hi> ſince he really wants, at leaſt for a time, that which he is forced to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for to another; and according to the old ſaying, He that goes a Borrowing, goes a Sorrowing. So that (with ſubmiſſion to better judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,) the meaning is this. — If thy Brother be impoveriſhed and weak of hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, If any Neighbour, though perhaps at other times of a conſiderable Competency, be ſo ſtraightened, that he needs thy aſſiſtance, either for <hi>ſaving</hi> or <hi>improving,</hi> by lawful means, what he already hath; or is <hi>Impoveriſhed,</hi> to witt, <hi>in danger to be impoveriſhed or undone,</hi> unleſs he have a ready ſum to lay down (which very ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al men have not always at hand, and on that conſideration may for the time be <hi>Poor.</hi>) Thou ſhalt lend him, if thou art able, or he give ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Surety for the Principal, or no notorious and undoubted diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage ariſe to thy ſelf thereby, without taking Uſe or <hi>More</hi> of him.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105386:8"/>
               <p>That this is the Genuine ſence of this place, appears from <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7. <hi>Si <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus de fratribus tuis,</hi> &amp;c. If one of thy Bre thren, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> come to Poverty, thou ſhalt not harden thy heart, nor cloſe thy hand, but ſhalt open it to the poor Man, and ſhalt lend him that which thou perceiveſt he hath need of; and <hi>v.</hi> 10. Neither ſhalt thou do any thing <hi>Craftily</hi> in relieving his Neceſſities, that our Lord thy God may bleſs thee at all times.</p>
               <p>From which places of <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. thus compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a very Learned Doctor thus argues. Pray what ſtrange Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is this, The Law forbids to take Uſe from a poor Man; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it permits us to receive it from the Rich? Let us examine a few Inferences of the like Nature, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.22. <hi>Viduae &amp; Pupillo non No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebitis,</hi> &amp;c. A Widdow and an Orphan you ſhall not hurt; if you hurt them, they will cry to Me, and I will hear their cry, and my Fury ſhall take Indignation, and I will ſtrike you with the Sword, and your Wives ſhall be Widdows, and your Children Orphans. Let us ſee a parallel Concluſion; we muſt not hurt the Widdow nor Orphan, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may deal as rigorouſly as we pleaſe with thoſe who have a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or a Husband. Again <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.18.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Maledictus qui errare facit caecum,</hi> &amp;c. Curſed be he that maketh the Blinde go amiſs in his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</q> But there is no harm done, if we put one that hath the uſe of his eyes, out of his way wittingly. Once more, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Non nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis mercedem indigentis,</hi> &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not deny the Hire of the Needy, but the ſame day ſhalt thou pay him the price of his Labour before the going down of the Sun, becauſe he is Poor, and therewithal ſuſtaineth his life, leſt he cry againſt thee to our Lord, and it be imputed to thee for Sin. Now in this Logick it will follow, that thoſe who are not in want, or have ſomething elſe to live upon, may without any ſcruple be defrauded of their wages.</p>
               <p>But the forecited place of <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.7. If one of thy Brethren come to Poverty, thou ſhalt not harden thy heart; thou ſhalt lend him that, which thou perceiveſt he hath need of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> affords us an unanſwereable ſolution to this Objection. The Text commands us to Lend to the <hi>Poor;</hi> therefore we muſt Lend to none but the <hi>Poor,</hi> (I hope they will acknowledge their own Concluſion.) The Law forbids to take Intereſt of the <hi>Poor,</hi> therefore only with the <hi>Poor</hi> we may not exerciſe Uſury. Now if we muſt lend only to the <hi>Poor</hi> (as by their Argument we muſt) and Uſury exacted from the <hi>Poor,</hi> (even our Adverſaries being Judges) is unlawful, ſince we muſt lend only to the <hi>Poor;</hi> it inevitably follows that all Uſury is unlawful.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105386:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> ſeems to plead thus in behalf of Uſurers. The Rich have a greater ſtock, and therefore may without dammage ſpare ſo much as the Intereſt comes to. His words are, <hi>Eſt ditior, &amp; poteſt abſque damno carere.</hi> But pray, ſaies the forementioned Learned Man, is not this to Patronize Rogues and Thieves? Will not the ſame excuſe ſerve the Robber as well as the Uſurer? He is a Monied or a Landed Man, and and can without much Inconvenience, part with ſo much as I take. But let him be Poor or Rich, Theft is in its own Nature unlawful. No leſs is Uſury, which is a kinde of Thievery. Yet is neither unjuſtifiable for the quantity or ſum, whether great or ſmall; but by reaſon of thoſe words of the Law, as fatal to Uſury as Robbery, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.17. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que omnia, quae illius ſunt. Thou ſhalt not Covet thy Neighbours Wife,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nor any thing that is his.</hi> But thoſe things are his which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by his Induſtry and hazard, and we muſt all eat the Labours of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn hands.</p>
               <p>Thus far he. And I have the rather in a manner tranſcribed ſo much, becauſe the Author (Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi>) is generally eſteemed one of the moſt Learned Prelats the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England</hi> ever injoy'd; and beſides this, he writes as it were by way of Apology in defence of his Church, which he acknowledges was taxed (though unjuſtly as he conceives) by Catholicks abroad, for allowing, if not teaching this doctrine of the Lawfulneſs of Uſury; ſo that he ſeems to ſpeak the mind of the whole <hi>Church of England.</hi> And I have inſiſted the longer upon theſe two places, becauſe they were ſubject to exceptions. But amends ſhall be made in what follows; for they are ſo clear from any captious Cavils, that to recount them will be ſufficient both for <hi>Proof</hi> and <hi>Explaining.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Divine Authority is, from <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Non faenerabis fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trituo ad uſuram,</hi> &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not lend to thy Brother, Money to Uſury, nor Corn, nor any other thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; to thy Brother thou ſhalt lend that which he needeth, without Uſury, that our Lord thy God may bleſs thee in all thy work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here the Caſe is plain, for there is no mention either of <hi>Poor</hi> or of <hi>Tyrannical Exaction;</hi> but the act it ſelf abſolutely and generally prohibited, both as to perſons and things, either in Quality, Money, Corn, or any thing elſe; or in Quantity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Uſury, that is, as I before demonſtrated, without Receiving <hi>More</hi> than was delivered. And it is worth our Notice that this book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> being but an Exegetical or declaratory Repetition of the Law of <hi>Exodus,</hi> as it were to prevent thoſe ſhifts that might be made;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105386:9"/>wholly omits the putting in of <hi>Poor,</hi> or <hi>Exacting</hi> too much; to teach us that the thing was indifferently denyed to all perſons, Rich and Poor; and that in the leaſt quantity, ſix ſhillings as well as ſix pound for the hundred. For the Rule of Lawyers, is, that therefore later Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes are made, that they may explain the former.</p>
               <p>That great Patron and Reſtorer of the <hi>Jews,</hi> good <hi>Nehemias</hi> moſt ſharply taxes this vice, and ſpares not to reprove the <hi>Princes</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, 2 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 5.7. (or according to the Engliſh account, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.7.) I was, ſayes he, exceeding Angry, and rebuked the Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and ſaid to them, <hi>Do you every one exact <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren?</hi> &amp;c. The thing is not good which you do. Why walk you not in the fear of our God, leſt we be upbraided by all the Gentiles our Enemies? <hi>Reddite eis hodie agros ſuos, quin &amp; centeſimam pecuniae,</hi> Reſtore their Fields and Vinyards, yea the hundreth part alſo of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Corn, Wine and Oyl, which you were wont to exact of them. Where we ſee ſo petty a matter as the hundreth part, not only condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as contrary to the fear of God, who had forbidden it; but even Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution enjoyned, as of goods unjuſtly purchaſed, and the practice cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured as ſcandalous to the very Heathen.</p>
               <p>The Royal Prophet <hi>David</hi> in his 14th. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> having propoſed the Queſtion to God Almighty, about the Qualifications requiſite for the attaining Eternal Felicity; <hi>Lord, who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle, or who ſhall reſt in thy Holy Hill?</hi> God himſelf in the fifth verſe returns an Anſwer, which may be called the Uſurers Doom. <hi>He that ſweareth to his Neighbour and deceiveth not; Qui pecuniam ſuam non dedit ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> who hath not given his Money to Uſury. Upon which words St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> thus argues. <hi>Si ergo qui non dedit, Benedictus; ſine dubio Maledictus qui ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram dedit:</hi> If he be bleſſed who hath not put out to Uſe, without doubt he is Curſed that drives that trade. If he who hath not done it, ſhall aſcend to Gods <hi>Holy Hill</hi> of everlaſting <hi>Happineſs:</hi> He that is guilty ſhall queſtionleſs be precipitated into the bottomleſs <hi>Gulfe</hi> of endleſs <hi>Miſeries.</hi> I might here Curſorily take notice that ſome Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks have obſerved, that not only the Uſurers final <hi>Damnation</hi> is here aſſerted, but the temporal <hi>Anathema,</hi> or <hi>Excommunication</hi> from the Church Militant is more than glanced at; ſince he is neither permitted to dwell in Gods <hi>Tabernacle</hi> or <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> nor to reſt in his <hi>Holy Hill,</hi> or <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> in the <hi>Jeruſalem that is above.</hi> But of his Excommunication.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105386:9"/>
               <p>From the Father, who was a man after Gods own heart, let us paſs to the Son, who was the Wifeſt of Men; I mean from <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſee what his thoughts are in this buſineſs, and we ſhall find that the Uſurers Condition is as bad in this World, as it is threaten'd to be in the next, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Qui coacervat Divitas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuris &amp; faenore,</hi> &amp;c. He that heapeth up Riches by Uſury, gathereth them for him that is liberal to the Poor. A moſt remarkable Curſe upon the Uſurer, that what he ſcrapes together ſhall never take root, or continue in his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but be <hi>tranſplanted</hi> by way of Gratuity to the Generation of the Merciful and Charitable.</p>
               <p>As Uſury is very pernicious to the <hi>Outward Eſtate</hi> thus managed, for it is no leſs fatal to the <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> of the Profeſſors. Theſe Publicans contracting a general Odium and Malediction, which multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies faſter than their bags, in ſo much that quite contrary to a right Patriot and Friend to Man-kinde, the Uſurer lives more by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Tears than his own Sweat, and dyes with the Tryumphs of all that know him. A man would ſtand aſtoniſhed at that Complaint of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> chapt. 15.10. <hi>Vaemihi,</hi> &amp;c. Woe is me, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, why haſt thou borne me, a man of brawling, a man of diſcord in all the Earth? I have not lent to Uſury, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet—all Curſe me. The good Prophet is in amazement how his name came to be ſo blaſted with popular Infection; and cannot imagine that the Vileſt Wretch ſhould become ſo loath ſome and nauſeous to his Brethren, but by that deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſperſion of Uſury, on which an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Curſe</hi> ſeems to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayled, which Vice he knew and proclaimed himſelf wholly untainted withal.</p>
               <p>But of all the heavy Judgments <hi>denounced</hi> in Gods Word by his own mouth, <hi>ſeconded</hi> by a ſolemn Oath, and <hi>back'd</hi> with a moſt vehement Repetition, that ſeems to be levell'd with moſt Terrour at the Uſurers head which we find <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.7, 8, 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and indeed well-nigh through the whole Chapter; where firſt for his greater glory he is ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe, who lift up their eyes to Idols, Violate their Neighbours Wife, approach to a Menſtruous Woman, make the Poor and Needy ſorrowful, (either by Uncharitableneſs or Oppreſſion,) Violently commit Robberies, (that is by ſheding of blood as the Context ſeems to inſinuate,) reſtore not the Pledge, do Abomination. And then in the Rear of this Black Regiment comes up, <hi>Ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram dantem &amp; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius accipientem,</hi> who giveth to Uſury, or taketh <hi>More,</hi> as if this were the ſum of all the reſt. Then this Indictment being thus found good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105386:10"/>and valid, the diſmal ſentence is at laſt paſſed, <hi>v.</hi> 13. What, ſhall ſuch an one live? He ſhall not live. <hi>Cum haec deteſtanda fecerit, Morie Morietur,</hi> Whereas he hath done theſe deteſtable things, he ſhall dye the death, his blood ſhall be upon him. This, me thinks, if duly pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſhould make the Uſurers heart ake, his haire briſtle, his joynts tremble, and himſelf become a horrour to himſelf; or as the Prophet ſpeaks, a <hi>Terrour round about him.</hi> For as ſure as God ſpeaks theſe things, ſo ſure is he to feel them (if he make not Reſtitution) with ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Rigour and Extremity.</p>
               <p>God by the ſame Prophet, <hi>chap.</hi> 22. 12. ſpeaks much to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Munera acceperunt upud te,</hi> &amp;c They have taken guifts in thee to ſhed blood, thou haſt taken Uſury and Overplus, and thou haſt forgotten me, ſaith our Lord God. As if he had ſaid, Thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that I have ſo punctually and univerſally forbid and threatened this Unconſionable practice. To which may be added, that Uſury is here compared with the forgetting of God, which in Scripture phraſe is the <hi>Imprimis, Item</hi> and total ſum, the very ſource and original of Sin and miſchief.</p>
               <p>Thus I have, as briefly as the matter would permit, from the Holy Writings of the Old Teſtament, underſtood according to the judgment of the Holy Fathers, moſt learned Expoſitors, and Sacred Councils, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the ſence of the Divine Law in point of Uſury. And I think you will confeſs them ſo diametrically oppoſite, that it will be an equal task to reconcile Idolatry with the firſt Commandment, and the <hi>Common Trade of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> with the <hi>Righteous Law of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And leſt we ſhould flatter our ſelves, that <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by Chriſt, and held forth in the Goſpel, diſingages us from all thoſe Legal Comminations and diſpenſes with the ſtrictneſs of theſe prohibitions: We muſt obſerve (and this without looking through the Spectacles of our proper temporal Intereſt) that our Bleſſed Saviour at the very entrance into his Preaching, publickly proteſts that he came not to deſtroy or evacuate the Law, but to compleat and perfect it; as might be inſtanced in divers particulars from St. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.18.22. &amp;c. You have heard, ſayes he, it was ſaid to them of Old, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Kill,</hi> but I ſay unto you, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be angry with his Brother, ſhall be in danger of Judgment;</hi> And whoſoever ſhall ſay, <hi>Thou Fool, ſhall be in danger of Hell Fire.</hi> You have heard it was ſaid to them of old, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Commit Adultery:</hi> But I ſay to you, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall look on a Woman to Luſt after her, hath already committed Adultery
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105386:10"/>with her in his heart:</hi> You have heard it was ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour and Hate thine Enemy:</hi> But I ſay to you, <hi>Love your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, do good to them that Hate you, Pray for them that Abuſe you,</hi> &amp;c. And as to our particular Caſe, it is moſt evident he was ſo far from abrogating the Laws then in force, that he rather inculcates, ratifies and ſtrongly confirms them both by his Doctrine and Practice.</p>
               <p>By his Doctrine, thus St. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.32. If you love them that love you, what thanks have you? for Sinners alſo love thoſe who love them. And if you do good to them who do good to you, what thanks have you? Sinners alſo do the ſame. And if you lend to them of whom you hope to receive, what thanks is it to you? For Sinners alſo lend to Sinners, for to receive as much. But love you your Enemies; do good and lend, hoping for nothing thereby (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umdate, nihil inde ſperantes</hi>) and your Reward ſhall be great, and you. ſhall be Sons of the Higheſt, becauſe he is beneficial to the unkinde and evil. <hi>Be ye therefore Merciful, as your Father in Heaven is Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From which Heavenly diſcourſe is fairly Inferred,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the matter of Uſury ſtands upon the ſame terms under Goſpel diſpenſation, as it did in the Moſaical. I ſay the <hi>ſame</hi> at leaſt, as to the buſineſs of cancelling, though perhaps otherwiſe more ſtrictly interdicted than before, upon manifold Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That Lending is a work of Mercy, and therefore ſhould be free (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.26. <hi>Tota die miſeretur &amp; Commodat, &amp; ſemen illius in benedictione erit.</hi> All the day (that is upon all occaſions) he is Merciful and Lendeth, and his Seed ſhall be in Bleſſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.5. <hi>Acceptable is the Man that is Merciful and Lendeth; Jucundus homo,</hi> as the Vulgar reads it.) For as <hi>Giving</hi> is a relief of our Neighbours ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for ever, ſo <hi>Lending</hi> is Relief for a time; and this is the only Circumſtance that diſtinguiſhes them. Nay in ſome ſence, Lending is a higher Act of Charity than Giving. For, in Lending I incourage the Party to Labour and Induſtry, that he may be able to repay me the Stock or Principal at the time aſſigned; whereas in Almes-giving, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to the pleaſure of the Relieved, as to its diſpoſal, who may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abuſe it and ſquander it idly away, knowing he is no further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable. Whence I conclude, that Lending in its <hi>Primary Notion</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> importing a ſingular Act of Charity (as it is ſenſibly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by thoſe, who being to ſet up for themſelves, enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of five or ten pounds, for ſo many years without any Intereſt, only
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105386:11"/>putting in ſufficient Security for the Principal; and they are worthily reckon'd among choyce Benefactors, who bequeath ſums of Money to ſuch pious Employments;) and Charity if you will believe St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſeeketh not her own; it neceſſarily follows, that by Lending to my own Profit (for where is there one in ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that either chiefly deſigns the benefit of the Borrower, or ſo much as inquires whether he hath made any?) I commit both <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Simony;</hi> by alienating what was deſigned by the Law of God, Nature and Nations to the profit of my Brother, from him to my own Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and ſelling a pretended Courteſie to him (which is likewiſe full of hazard) for a real and unqueſtionable (morally ſpeaking) advantage to my ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That the ſtyle of the New Law runs thus; We are in our Lending not ſo much as to <hi>hope for any thing thereby;</hi> that is to ſay, any thing more than our own, or what we Lent. For our Saviour ſpeaks not here of <hi>Giving,</hi> which is an entire quitting of all Right and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to the thing beſtowed, and that for ever; but of <hi>Lending,</hi> which neceſſarily involves both a Right of demanding, and an Obligation of repaying what was disburſed. So that by Lending and hopeing for nothing thereby, cannot be underſtood an Evangelical Counſel, or matter of indifferency, as if we ſhould Lend and expect nothing again, not ſo much as the Principal, for this would not be <hi>Lending</hi> but pure <hi>Guift;</hi> but a Precept of Charity to ſupply the wants of our Neighbour for a time (when we cannot conveniently for good and all) if it may be done without eminent prejudice to our ſelves (for all the Commands of aſſiſting the Poor oblige no further) and not ſo much as hope, have an eye or the leaſt regard and reſpect to ſelf-Intereſt, which may accrue upon the ſcore of Lending; which is properly to hope for nothing <hi>thereby,</hi> namely <hi>by</hi> the act of Lending, but only the ſatisfaction to have done our Neighbour a Courteſie, which I confeſs by the Law of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude he is bound to acknowledge, and (if his Improvements have been notable) in ſome meaſure to repay; but by the Law of God I can neither bargain for, nor exact upon the bare account of Lending.</p>
               <p>To cloſe this Argument; I think this Dilemma is unanſwerable. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Lord and Saviour, when he bids us <hi>do good and Lend, hoping for nothing thereby,</hi> impoſes ſome duty upon us, or his words were to no purpoſe, and ſignifie nothing. To affirm the latter is little better than Blaſphemy, ſince he himſelf ſo ſolemnly proclaimes that <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away but one</hi> Iota <hi>or Tittle of his Words ſhall not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105386:11"/>paſs.</hi> If he layes any Obligation upon us, then either it is, that we ſhould lend, and hope for nothing, not ſo much as the Principal, and this is more than I urge, or the Defenders of Intereſt will willingly hearken to; or elſe, we muſt lend and hope for nothing by way of Augmentation or Overplus, over and above what was delivered. One of theſe Interpretations muſt be faſtened upon theſe words, or elſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nothing will be <hi>Terminus Impertinens</hi> as the School ſpeaks, and ſtand for as much as the Advice, juſt <hi>nothing at all.</hi> And now I leave the Uſurer to his choyce; let him take which Expoſition he pleaſes, one of them he cannot avoyd.</p>
               <p>This for the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Bleſſed Jeſus, to which his practice was conformable, though with ſome difference; that what he only diſſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in words, he ſeverely puniſhed in his actions, as may be Collected from the 2 of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, <hi>v.</hi> 14. where we read, that <hi>Jeſus finding in the Temple them who ſold Oxen, Sheep, and Doves;</hi> and the <hi>Bankers</hi> (<hi>Numularios,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is St. <hi>Matthew's</hi> word) <hi>Thoſe who ſat with ready Money for ſuch who would Borrow)</hi> ſitting, <hi>he made a whip of ſmall Cords, and caſt them all out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the Money of the Bankers he poured out, and the Tables he overthrew.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> indeed reports that he ſaid only to the Sellers of Oxen, Sheep and Doves, <hi>Take away theſe things from hence, and make not the Houſe of my Father, a Houſe of Merchandize.</hi> But St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> chap. 21. 13. recounting the ſame Hiſtory, adds, that he threw them out of the Temple with this ſmart ſarcaſme, <hi>My Houſe ſhall be called the Houſe of Prayer, but you have made it</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>a Den of Thieves.</hi> Now thoſe who bought and ſold could not properly be ſtiled Thieves, ſince in it ſelf, buying or ſelling is an honeſt Vocation; and therefore it is more than probable that St. <hi>John</hi> only mentions what he ſaid to the Buyers and Sellers of Oxen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but St. <hi>Matthew</hi> adjoyns what was particularly addreſſed to the Bankers or Uſurers; and ſhews that our Saviour made no diſtinction between their Profeſſion and that of common Rogues. And yet as we may diſcover from the Hebrew Antiquities, theſe Bankers only accepted of ſome ſmall preſent, as fruits or ſome ſuch like Commodity, for the uſe of their Money, far leſs conſiderable, and indeed nothing in reſpect of what is demanded now adays.</p>
               <p>It would not be beſides the purpoſe to reflect here with many Holy Fathers and great Doctors, how our Saviour by driving Uſurers out of the material Temple, did leave a ſufficient Authority for the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105386:12"/>Prelates of his Church, to exclude them from the <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> by Excommunication, as is to this day, and hath for many hundred years been practiſed in Catholick Countries by Eccleſiaſtical Canons.</p>
               <p>Let me deal ingeniouſly with you; either our Bleſſed Saviour in theſe two places ſo much inſiſted on, did abſolutely forbid the practice of Uſury; or we muſt confeſs that at leaſt in this point the Goſpel falls ſhort of the Law and Charity (which yet breaths in every line of the Goſpel) is more coldly preſſed in <hi>This</hi> than <hi>That,</hi> which in effect is to make Chriſtians worſe than Jews, and affirm that Chriſtians are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more unconſcionable Exactions from one another, than was ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Moſaical Occonomie; which aſſertion, how offenſive it would prove to pious Ears, and diſcreditable to our Religion both with Jews and Heathens, I leave it to your good judgment, <hi>Madam,</hi> to conceive more amply than I can repreſent.</p>
               <p>Before I diſmiſs this Motive of the Divine Prohibition, it will be worth the while to prevent a double Objection; one is produced out of the Old Teſtament, the other out of the New.</p>
               <p>The former is from <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend thy Brother Money to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſed Alieno,</hi> but to a ſtranger. So that it ſeems U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is not intrinſecally, or in its own Nature Evil, for then the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it would have been indifferently denied towards <hi>All,</hi> the <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> as well as the <hi>Native</hi> or <hi>Inhabitant.</hi> But to this the Anſwer is Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious; for,</p>
               <p n="1">I. This favours not at all our <hi>Modern Money-Merchants,</hi> who take all fiſh that comes to Net; not diſtinguiſhing between Strangers and their own Brethren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since the coming of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> or the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the Wall of <hi>Partition</hi> between Jews and Gentiles, or Brethren and Strangers, is now pulled down, and both are made one, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>fecit utraque unum, medium parietom maceriae ſolvens,</hi>) we are now all one Flock under that <hi>great Shepherd</hi> of our Souls, and ſo all men are our Brethren, and the <hi>By-word</hi> of Strangers is wholly Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated, and conſequently Univerſally Interdicted.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By this Argument, ſtretch'd to the utmoſt, we could only take Uſe of Jews, Turks, and Inſidels, which I preſume our Bankers will not be content with,</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105386:12"/>
               <p n="4">4. I may ſpeak in this matter as our Saviour himſelf did in the point of Divorce, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.6, 7. He had told the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> that <hi>Man and Wife were not two, but one fleſh; and therefore what God had joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, no man could ſeparate.</hi> To this the Phariſes retort, <hi>Why then did</hi> Moſes <hi>command to give a Bill of Divorce and diſmiſs her?</hi> our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Anſwers, <hi>Becauſe</hi> Moſes <hi>for the</hi> hardneſs of your hearts (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>permitted you to diſmiſs your Wives, but from the Beginning it was not ſo.</hi> Thus becauſe the Jews, as it is ſtill obſerved, were of a penuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, griping, exacting Nature; to prevent a greater miſchief, namely of Uſury and Exaction, and conſequently of Contention, Law-ſuites and Ruining of Families among themſelves; for the <hi>hardneſs of their hearts</hi> God permitted them to take advantage of Strangers. Juſt as in hotter Climats, the Stews and Publick Brothels are tolerated, not as juſtifiable, but to divert the groſſer Crimes of Adultery, Sodomy and Beſtiality. And humane affairs are many times reduced to thoſe Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, that ſmaller offences force the Magiſtrate to connive at them on purpoſe to ſtave off more notable Enormities; of two Evils the leſs being always to be choſen. Nor doth this Doctrine infringe St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Rule of <hi>not doing Evil, that Good may come of it:</hi> For behaving ones ſelf <hi>purely permiſſively,</hi> or Negatively, <hi>i. e.</hi> not actually concurring to ſin, is not poſitive committing it, as appears by the Toleration of all the Extravagancies and Impieties acted upon the Worlds Theatre, which yet might be eaſily ſtopp'd, if the All-Wiſe Providence did not know how to extract greater Good out of them; which Reaſon, as it ſufficiently vindicates the <hi>Supreme Purity,</hi> ſo may it juſtifie <hi>Subordinate Authority,</hi> when neceſſitated upon the Emergencies of Humane Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Malice, to tranſcribe the Divine Original in its proceedings, and eſpecially when it hath not only <hi>hopes,</hi> but <hi>aſſured experience</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceing the ſame happy effects.</p>
               <p>The Indulgence then, or permiſſion of dealing after this faſhion with Strangers, was altogether Extraordinary, and much of the ſame Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with that grant God made them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 11.2. <hi>of Robbing and Spoyling the</hi> Aegyptians, <hi>under the pretence of Borrowing,</hi> which was a ſpecial act of Gods Perogative and Supreme Dominion to transfer Right whither, and to whom he pleaſes, and ſo both Impertinent to our purpoſe, and the like Conſequences moſt pernicious to be reduced to practice. Moreover you will perceive by the ſequel of this Diſpute, that the Authorities and Reaſons hereafter to be alleaged (as the Texts of Holy Scripture already produced have done) as forceably conclude againſt wronging a Stranger as our Brother.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105386:13"/>
               <p>The other Pretext that Uſury palliates her deformity withal, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from one of our Saviours Parables, St. <hi>Math.</hi> 25.14. &amp;c. where he ſpeaks of a man that was going into a far Country, and delivered his Goods to his Servants, that they might Traffick; to one he gives five Talents, to another two, and to the third one: The firſt Traded, and made his five Talents ten; the other likewiſe advanced his couple to four; but the laſt digging in the Earth, hid his Maſters Money: Now at the return of their Lord, the two former for their diligence are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed with an <hi>Euge ſerve bone &amp; fidelis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Well done Good and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant, enter into the joy of thy Lord;</hi> whereas the third, though he faithfully reſtored what he had received, and that entire, without the leaſt embezlement, yet for not employing his one Talent proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the others five and two, meets with this terrible Sentence, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Serve male &amp; Piger,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou Wicked and Sloathful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, thou oughteſt to have committed my Money to the Bankers, that coming home, I might have received my own with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury. Caſt ye out the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Teeth.</hi>—Here our Money-mongers think their profeſſion not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tolerated, but highly applauded by Chriſt's own Approbation.</p>
               <p>Truly at the firſt propoſal of this place, I knew not well whether the Objector were in earneſt or jeſt; for the Conſequences of it are ſo monſtrouſly abſurd, that I could not conceive it poſſible for any ſerious man to put ſuch an Application or Conſtruction upon it. Yet occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally finding that <hi>Ameſius</hi> (otherwiſe no unlearned Clerk) makes uſe of this very Text to countenance what I now plead againſt, I ſhall reply ſomthing to what elſe would probably have produced nothing but my ſmile.</p>
               <p n="1">1. And to omit that known Maxim in Divinity, <hi>Parabola vel ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo non eſt Argumentativa.</hi> No ſolid concluſion can be drawn from Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical or Allegorical premiſes; if they be not elſe-where clearly <hi>(terminis terminantibus)</hi> delivered. For why might I not as well juſtifie a Servants cheating his Maſter, from the Alluſion to the unjuſt Steward in <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.1.2. &amp;c. as Uſury from this Reference to the Talents? I am ſure the Circumſtances are parallel, and the Bayliffe is as highly commended for reckoning but fourſcore quarters of Wheat to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter inſtead of an hundred, as here the improvement of five Talents to ten, is <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Et laudavit Dominus Villicum Iniquitatis,</hi> &amp;c. And the Lord praiſed the Bayliffe of Iniquity, becauſe he had done wiſely. And then our B. Saviour ſubjoynes, <hi>For the Children of this World are Wiſer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105386:13"/>in their Generation than the Children of Light.</hi> I commend theſe two Parables to your ſerious peruſal, and I am confident you will eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, that if ſuch kind of Argumentations be allowed, the ſlie, pilfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Steward or Apprentice will finde as fair a Cloak for his Knavery in the latter, as the griping Miſer can in the former for his greedineſs.</p>
               <p>The ſum of the buſineſs is this; neither the one nor the other, can any ways pretend a Warrant for their proceedings from theſe two Scriptures; for <hi>ſimile non eſt Idem:</hi> In every Similitude or Parable, one thing is expreſs'd to the Sence, &amp; another ſuggeſted to the Underſtanding. And therefore we muſt (unleſs we reſolve to miſtake in unridling ſuch obſcure ſpeeches) attend principally to the drift and ſcope of the propounder, which we ſhall find to be quite different from what is pretended. For the deſign of the Bleſſed Jeſus in the firſt of theſe Reſemblances, was only to inform us how dreadful a thing it is not to employ the very leaſt Talent, Guift or Grace of God to its proper uſe, His Glory, the good of our Neighbour, and the advantage of our own ſoul. So that it is <hi>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> that is here urged, and that by a conſideration <hi>a fortiori:</hi> If worldlings be ſo ſollicitous in improving their temporal, fading ſtock; and Carnal Maſters are ſo rigorous in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting an account of the profit and in-come redounding from the ſame; it neerly behoves us, who have all, more or leſs, received ſome Talent or other (as Learning, Strength, Beauty, Riches, Time; but above all, the ſaving knowledg of God reconciled to us through the blood of his Son,) from our Heavenly Father, not idly to lay it up in a Napkin, (which in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s judgment is the <hi>Receiving the Grace of God in vain</hi>) or Prodigally conſume it on our Luſts and Vanities, but to uſe it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to the intents and purpoſes aboveſaid, moſt certainly expecting to undergoe a ſevere Examin, both at the private <hi>Audit</hi> of our <hi>Death,</hi> and at the final <hi>Return</hi> of our <hi>Great Maſter</hi> to the General Judgment; when, if our ſcores be not quitted in this life, it is to be feared, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Ne forte tradat te Adverſarius,</hi> &amp;c. leſt the Adverſary deliver thee to the Judge, and the Judge to the Officer, and thou be caſt into Priſon. <hi>Amen,</hi> I ſay to thee, thou ſhalt not go thence, till thou haſt paid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum Quadrantem,</hi> the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing, St. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.26.</p>
               <p>The example of the Bayliffe of Iniquity, is near of kin to this, and both together teach us this great <hi>Leſſon:</hi> That if Bankers by Uſury, and unjuſt Stewards by Diſhoneſty, are ſo hotly ſet upon their outward affairs, though with manifeſt hazard of their ſouls, it will be a burning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105386:14"/>ſhame for Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, whoſe <hi>hopes</hi> are <hi>nobler,</hi> whoſe <hi>helps</hi> are <hi>ampler,</hi> and <hi>Obligations ſtricter,</hi> to be outſtript in the zeal and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of proſecuting their deſigns, ſince the eagerneſs of the one, and the craft of the other in ſo bad a cauſe, will riſe up in Judgment againſt our Indifferency and Tepidity in matters of grandeſt Importance.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, we have view'd our Saviours mind in clear words, and more clear actions before, and therefore it is a very pittiful evaſion to recurr to Myſteries and Oracles, ſince it is a moſt undoubted truth, that what was ſo ſolemnly condemned both by his <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi> cannot poſſibly now be authorized by a dark Parable. The litteral meaning whereof, I look upon as a <hi>Sea-mark</hi> to be avoyded, but the Moral as a <hi>Land-mark</hi> to be followed in our Journey to Heaven.</p>
               <p>This might ſatisfie any Ingenious diſintereſted Spirit; but that I may for ever ſtop the mouth of Avaricious Sophiſtry, I Anſwer:</p>
               <p>Secondly: If any thing at all can be deduced from this Parable, it muſt needs be theſe prodigious Paradoxes following, which I preſume the boldeſt Uſurer will never have the Confidence to own.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is an Indiſpenſable tye, and Obligation laid upon all without exception, to turn Uſurers <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Oportuit itaque,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou oughteſt to have committed my money to the Bankers.</hi> It is neither matter of permiſſion only, nor of meer indifferency.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Uſurers have, not only a Right to their Goods ſo purchaſed, (quite contrary to what was evinced before out of the Old Teſtament, and the main currant of the Catholick Church) but likewiſe to the Goods of all others who are not of their ſociety and profeſſion. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tollite itaque,</hi> &amp;c. Take away his Talent (to wit, who put it not out to the Bank) and give it to him that hath ten.</p>
               <p>But 3dly. The moſt ridiculous and unheard-of Inference is this, That none but Uſurers ſhall be ſaved. This naturally reſults from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Et Inutilem ſervum ejicite in tenebras exteriores.</hi> Caſt ye the unprofitable Servant into utter darkneſs, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: That is to ſay, in our Adverſaries ſence; He who knows not the <hi>thriving knack,</hi> and ſo cannot, or hath a ſquamiſh Conſcience, and will not thus <hi>increaſe</hi> and <hi>multiply</hi> five to ten, and two to four, gain ſix or ten to the hundred, muſt ee'n ſing <hi>Fortune my Foe</hi> in this World, and <hi>Lachrymae</hi> in the next, to the doleful tune of <hi>Gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> This is all that can with any ſhew of probability be gather'd hence, as to our preſent purpoſe; ſo that certainly, if ever, here <hi>Litera Occidit,</hi> the Letter kills; and ſomething of a nobler nature muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhrin'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105386:14"/>within the Curtains of this Oracle, which the Uſurer is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindful to practice, as he is averſe to hear. What it is, was before hinted.</p>
               <p>But theſe men being beaten from their <hi>Out-works,</hi> begin now to retire to their <hi>Cittadel.</hi> Since therefore they appeal to Reaſon, to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall they go.</p>
               <p>Though there remain little or nothing for humane Congruity to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage, when the Divine Will (that ſupreme Reaſon and Rule of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) remains ſo poſitive againſt what is here impugned. <hi>Stat pro Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one;</hi> and it ill becomes <hi>Children of Obedience</hi> to diſpute the <hi>Why</hi> and <hi>Wherefore</hi> of Soveraign Injunctions. Nay, did the Principles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience as much protect, as they do in reallity oppoſe, what ſome wiſh (for I can ſcarce perſwade my ſelf that they believe it) yet there being many things, as St. <hi>Aug.</hi> hath long ſince accurately obſerved, <hi>Ideo Mala, quia Prohibita; non ideo Prohibita quia mala,</hi> Evil only upon the account of being forbidden, not prohibited becauſe Evil of themſelves, (as appears by various inſtances, wherein the liberty of the Patriarches and Iſraelites was abridged, purely to experiment the complyance and conformity of inferiour Inclinations to the dictates of their Creator) theſe notifications of the Divine Pleaſure, even in Adiaphoricals or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different matters, ought as promptly to be acquieſced in, as if they were (as in truth they are) indiſſolubly twiſted with our neareſt concerns. Here at laſt <hi>blind Obedience</hi> carries away the Palme from fruitleſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiveneſs; I mean where the minde of the Eternal Law-giver is ſo expreſs, as we have ſeen, though perhaps abuſed Wit may pretend with ſome plauſibility, that there is a little jangling with the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous management of ſublunary tranſactions.</p>
               <p>We muſt not therefore attempt the reduceing of Divine Statutes to our ſhallow underſtandings and private concerns, but rather believe them infinitely juſt and reaſonable. Whereof, he that fees not the Reaſon, would do well to conſider, there may be a Reaſon which he does not ſee, and that it is not only poſſible, but uſual for finite In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellects to miſtake Luſt or Intereſt, for the Standard of Right and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whereas for the ſupreme minde to deviate, or the All powerful Will to be biaſſed, but by eſſential truth and goodneſs, is a contradiction in terms; that being the inexhauſted fountain of both, and by its Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations beſtowing Reallity and Coherence as well as Exiſtence on all Creatures; ſo that a thing is therefore true and good, becauſe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by this Immenſe and Un-obliquable Will. Whence it follows,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105386:15"/>that our only Lawful Scrutiny in this matter, is that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> at his Converſion, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Domine, quid me vis facere?</hi> Lord what <hi>Wilt</hi> thou have me to do? The eccho to the <hi>Creators</hi> commands, muſt be no other than the <hi>Creatures</hi> obedience.</p>
               <p>I argue after this manner; becauſe, ſhould I not be able to make out the unlawfulneſs of what I here contend againſt, ſo <hi>Demonſtratively</hi> as ſome may expect, (which perhaps the matter it ſelf will not beare;) yet the manifeſt intimation of that Law, from whence there is no appeal, which I am confident I have ſufficiently evinced, will <hi>ex abundante,</hi> as we ſay, conclude the <hi>Thing</hi> unreaſonable, and the <hi>Practiſers</hi> inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Indeed I ſcarce know any one Divine Precept, which corrupt Nature may not nibble at, nay at ſome time or other hath not quarrell'd with. The moſt effectual courſe to ſilence the debate, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Dixit Dominus,</hi> the Lord hath ſaid it; whom who can reſiſt and be guiltleſs? Now what He hath ſaid in the preſent buſineſs, hath been over and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cleared in the precedent Lines.</p>
               <p>However, that I may diſengage my promiſe, and leave no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of complaint to the Antagoniſts, it will be very well worth your while, <hi>Madam,</hi> to view how exactly Diſſintereſted Reaſon both cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponds with, and preſſes the Obſervance of the forementioned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition.</p>
               <p>I can hardly conceive but that all Indifferent perſons will eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover many Abſurdities immediatly conſequent upon the Hypotheſis of Uſuries Warrantableneſs; I ſhall conſult your patience, and therefore rather name, than proſecute ſome few which I find alleaged by the moſt learned and ſincere Writers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Lender reaps very notable advantage by that which is no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>his own.</hi> For I ſuppoſe, &amp; it hath been in part proved, that money, or any other thing Lent (as Caſulſts here uſe the word) is always made over, and is in the Right Poſſeſſion and Dominion of the Borrower for ſuch a terme of time. In which reſpect only, it differs from <hi>Gift,</hi> which conveys the ſaid Right and Dominion away for ever. This is moſt apparent, becauſe if the Money or Principale be loſt, it periſhes to the <hi>Borrower,</hi> and not to the <hi>Lender,</hi> who makes that ſure againſt all contingencies by transferring his Right as to all Intents to the ſaid Borrower for the time agreed upon. Neither is he able to call it in, or otherwayes diſpoſe of it, till that date is expired. All which, are moſt clear evidences that by Receiving Intereſts he partakes the benefit of that which is not his, and unconſionably requires to ſhare in the prize,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105386:15"/>without ever communicating in the hazard. Now how hard it is, and unreaſonable for me to make my markets of that which is ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking anothers Commodity, is obvious enough to any one who duly conſiders it. Hence ariſes a general Rule, that <hi>every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or burthen annexed to Lending, except ſuch as is proper and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſical to it, renders the contract <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The end of Money is perfectly abuſed: For <hi>That,</hi> by vertue of its primary Inſtitution is the Univerſal Inſtrument of Commerce, and the common means of exchanging other Wares. But the Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſells Money for Money, very prepoſterouſly confounding the Merchandiſe and the price together.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Uſurer ſells that which is his duty by a three-fold Law of Nature, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and Grace. By the Law of Nature, the Rich are obliged to lend to the Poor: (I underſtand, when they cannot conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently give out right,) for that teaches us to do to others, as we would be done to our ſelves. Now I refer it to the Conſcience of whom you pleaſe, whether they themſelves had not much rather borrow, when forc'd by neceſſity, without other Tye, but of Thanks and the Principal, than even of 3 <hi>per cent.</hi> By <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, the Rich were ſeverely Commanded to aſſiſt the Poor by Lending <hi>Gratis.</hi> And what our Saviours Judgment is, appears by what hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed before, but more fully from St. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.42. <hi>Qui petit a te, da ei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Give to him that asks of thee, and turn not away from him that would borrow;</hi> and in all this, <hi>Nihil inde ſperantes;</hi> we muſt hope for nothing again. Surely the Poor are little beholding to theſe Laws, if they meant only that there ſhould indeed lye a ſtrong Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the Rich to Relieve them, either by <hi>Giving</hi> or <hi>Lending;</hi> but withal, they ſhould pay dear for it, by returning a great deal more than ever they received, to ſtuff up the Uſurers Coffers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Uſurer acts in compleat Contradiction to Nature and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and that upon divers accounts. For <hi>Accommodare eſt ad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum Proximi dare, &amp; Dare Mutuum, eſt Dare Meum ut ſit Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> To Lend, is to profit my Neighbour, or do him a Courteſie. But the Uſurer pretending to do this, mindes nothing leſs, granting an <hi>uncertain</hi> (either for ſubſtance or quantity) and <hi>future</hi> profit to the Borrower, but reſerving a morally infallible and fix'd Benefit to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Again, Money is of a barren Nature, in token whereof, the metal is formed by Nature in the moſt ſterile, inhabitable places,—
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105386:16"/>
                  <hi>(Itum eſt in Viſcera Terrae—Effodiuntur Opes—)</hi> Now to <hi>bring forth the ſame ſpecies,</hi> is proper only to things indued with life. Yet in ſpite of God and Nature, the Uſurer will make his Money fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that without Intermiſſion, day and night, Winter and Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and will have it work and improve, whilſt he himſelf takes his eaſe and reſt. Beſides all this, he moſt audaciouſly attempts upon that High Prerogative of God, <hi>Creation,</hi> or producing Something out of Nothing; for 100 <hi>l.</hi> can be worth but an 100 <hi>l.</hi> wherefore the 6. or more for Intereſt, muſt neceſſarily be the product of <hi>Nothing.</hi> Or as the great Lawyer <hi>Baldas</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer indeavours Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities,</hi> that One ſhould be more than One, a 100 <hi>l.</hi> ſhould be an 106 <hi>l.</hi> nay in time 200 <hi>l.</hi> He receives profit from that which is not, nor perhaps will ever be, and therefore ſells to the Borrower either <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Nothing,</hi> or the <hi>ſame thing twice,</hi> or the <hi>Borrowers proper Labour and Induſtry.</hi> All which actions are moſt unjuſt and intollerable, as I might eaſily amplifie in every particular, but that I relinquiſh to your own pregnant Imagination, abundantly able to ſupply what is here rudely ſhuffled together and ſlubberd over. The utmoſt that can be ſaid is, he doth <hi>ſpem pretio vendere,</hi> ſell the hope of very uncertain gain, which is not <hi>yet,</hi> and God alone knows whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ever <hi>will</hi> be, for moſt aſſured profit; which by the Heathen themſelves was eſteemed injurious in a high degree. For <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf by the Light of Nature, 1 <hi>Politic. c.</hi> 7. could inform us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Uſury ſaies he, is Money of Money, and therefore this ſort of gain is directly againſt Nature. Hence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pario,</hi> and <hi>Foenus a Foetu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Uſurer violates Gods Law continually, without the leaſt Ceſſation either as to Time or Place; in which regard he may be ſtiled an <hi>Everlaſting Offendor.</hi> Nay he commits his Tranſgreſſions in an hundred ſeveral places together ſometimes, to wit, when his Money is breeding in ſo many diſtant Banks. The Fornicator hath his <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> at certain ſeaſons, nor is he wholly taken up in the <hi>Tents of Venus.</hi> The good Fellow hath his lucid and ſerious Intervals. Only the Uſurer both ſleeping and waking, night and day, in his Chamber &amp; a Church, Praying and Playing, is ſtill <hi>trading, brooding,</hi> and <hi>hatching</hi> more Money, without the leaſt reſpite, and thus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> threatens, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.) he <hi>Treaſures up</hi> every moment to himſelf, Wrath againſt the day of Wrath.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105386:16"/>
               <p n="6">6. The Uſurer hath leſs Charity to his fellow Chriſtian, than a Jew to his Brother Jew; for a Jew durſt not offer to take one penny Intereſt from one of his own Religion. This may ſeem a weak Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, but it is our Saviour's own motive in the fore-mentioned ſixth Chapter of St. <hi>Luke.</hi> If you lend to them of whom you hope to receive, what thanks have ye? <hi>Nam &amp; pecatores peccatoribus ſenerantur, ut recipiant aequalia,</hi> For even Sinners lend to Sinners, that they may receive equal. For ſhame, Chriſtians, let not Publicans and Sinners, nay Jews riſe up in Judgment againſt us; for they lend, and only expect <hi>Aequalia</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an equal ſum to what they lent, (if you will Credit Truth it ſelf, who avouches ſo) whereas Profeſſors of, and Pretenders to the Doctrine of this great Maſter, will not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure one another, without exacting their own and much more into the bargain.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All the Uſurers goods are Monſtrous, <hi>Dentata,</hi> ſull of Teeth, and Claws to prey upon his Neighbour. His Corn, which was created by God to be the Food of Man, in lieu thereof, eats up thoſe who borrow and make uſe of it, and ſo of the reſt. This in effect is the ſence of thoſe frequent complaints we meet with, <hi>I owe</hi> 50, 60, <hi>or</hi> 100 <hi>l. the very uſe whereof conſumes and devours me! I could of ten have refunded the main, but being rejected, becauſe not attended by the Acceſſory or Intereſt, that now hath even ſurmounted the former? I failed but one day, and was forced to renew my Leaſe, and ſubmit my neck to the yoak of another ſix moneths Exaction, though both Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Principal were faithfully tendered! Oh the corroding, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring expenſes of Procuration, Continuation,</hi> &amp;c! <hi>under which I now groan!</hi> Theſe, with the like grievous moans and ſighs of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Families, make me ready to burſt forth into his Exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Aut hoc non eſt Evangelium, aut Nos non ſumus Chriſtiani!</hi> Either the Texts before alleaged, are not Scripture and Goſpel, or we who practice the contrary are hardly <hi>Chriſtians!</hi> And whereas in the Primitive Age, the very <hi>Badge</hi> and <hi>Characteriſtical note</hi> of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, was <hi>Ecce, quomodo ſe invicem diligunt Chriſtiani!</hi> Behold, ſaid the Infidels, how theſe Chriſtians Love one another! I fear it it would be now underſtood but <hi>Ironically,</hi> or rather alter'd of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty into its contrary, as matter of the World's aſtoniſhment; Behold how theſe mock-Chriſtians Trappan and ſwallow up one another! Nay, more like a Canibal than civiliz'd Creature, the Uſurer eats up
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105386:17"/>the very heart of the Labours, drinks the tears and ſweat of the poor with a great deal of guſt, content and jocundneſs.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Money, as I have obſerv'd elſe-where, is reducible to thoſe things, the Right or Dominion whereof is inſeparable from the uſe. I can no more Uſe Money without parting with it, than Victuals without eating them. Wherefore as he would be deſervedly eſteemed a man of ſtrange principles, who for a loaf of bread ſhould firſt ask me the true value for it, and after that was paid, demand ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable for my <hi>uſing</hi> or <hi>eating</hi> it; ſo it ſeems little leſs Exaction to Lend money, and have the ſame again at ſuch a time; and yet not to be content with this, but over and above expect and extort ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> or <hi>ſpending</hi> of it. Thus in truth it is, for I challenge any one Banker among ten thouſand, who dares ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg that he either bargains only for an equitable ſhare in the Adventure or Purchaſe, or ſo much as inquires whether a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Return was made or no; nay, whether the Stock or Principal it ſelf did not utterly miſcarry, or at leaſt fall ſhort to the expectation of the Employer, who is bound faſt enough by Wax, Parchment and Friends, both for the payment of that, and ſomething elſe.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In all Contracts or Bargains, three Circumſtances are very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively to be heeded, Labour, Charge, and Danger. But with which of theſe doth the Uſurer ſo much as concern himſelf? All theſe Incumbrances lye on the back of the Borrower. As for the Labour and Pains, let the Uſurer ſtand, ſit, ſleep, laugh, eat and drink,; whole weeks, months, and years run on, and the Uſe keeps even pace with them. So that in flat defiance of <hi>In ſudore vultus tui veſceris pane,</hi> In the ſweat of <hi>thy</hi> brows thou ſhalt eat thy bread, (which was the heavy penalty laid on all the Children of <hi>Adam</hi>) he is reſolved only to dip his in that of his Neighbours. Then as to the charge and coſt, that is altogether the Borrowers, the Lender ventures not one penny. The danger likewiſe is only his; for if the Stock faile, the Debtor is Reſponſible, whereas the Creditor is ſecured all the ways that humane Wit, Policy, and Law can invent, to make him ſafe, by Bonds, Witneſſes, Sureties, and I know not what. Now what Lawful profit is to be made, that is not conjoyned with one or more of theſe three? the Uſurer medles with none of them.</p>
               <p>I foreſee what will be replyed, and it is in every man's mouth, <hi>Damnum ex Lucro Ceſſante,</hi> He ſuffers loſs by reaſon of the Gain
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105386:17"/>that ceaſeth by not having the Money in his own hands. This is the Uſurers thread-bare plea. But, pray what manner of loſs is this that is alleaged? The loſs of a poſſible gain is ſufficiently recompenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a poſſible loſs that is avoyded. This I am confident of, that did any know how to make greater or equal advantage by retayning their Money in their own poſſeſſion, the Borrower ſhould never have the trouble of it. Here then lies the ſweet of Uſury; the Money, morally ſpeaking, is far ſafer in other mens hands than our own; for what Bonds or Security have we from Thieves, Fire, and other Caſualties of all ſorts? all which by this trick of Lending, are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently warded off; beſides a certain <hi>delicious morſel</hi> which muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company home the Principal to make it more welcome.</p>
               <p>By which way of proceeding, the Uſurer falls very near within the Verge of Atheiſme, totally as it were ſubſtracting himſelf from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; for what need he depend upon the Influences of Heaven, pray for rain, fair weather, or other bleſſings, ſince all is one to him? Let it ſhower or ſhine, he knows his Debtor is acquainted with his day prefixt, which if he fayle, the greateſt mercy to be look'd for, is, either the Goale, Forfeiture of a Mortgage, or a diſmal Continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the former devouring Courteſie, from time to time, to his final Ruine.</p>
               <p n="10">10. I might urge the very nature of Lending, which as hath been declared in its eſſential notion, ſpeaks <hi>Gratuitouſneſs,</hi> and is one of the works of Corporal Mercy, chiefly reſpecting the Temporal good of another, providing only for mine own Indemnity. Whereas in the Uſurers practice, it is clean perverted to the contrary, my <hi>own</hi> Convenience, and my <hi>Brothers</hi> Prejudice.</p>
               <p>But for brevity ſake, I ſhal pretermit that, with ſundry other weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Reaſons, and wind up all with this convincing one. It is a moſt ſolemne and indiſpenſable Statute, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.36. <hi>Nolite facere iniquum aliquid in pondere, in menſura. Statera juſta &amp; aequa ſint pondera; Ego Dominus Deus veſter:</hi> Do nothing unjuſt in weight, or meaſure; let the ballance be juſt, and the weights equal; I am the lord your God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſubſume, but Money now by general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is the <hi>Common Standard</hi> or <hi>meaſure of Exchange.</hi> How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt then muſt the Uſurer be, who makes the <hi>meaſure</hi> it ſelf, whence all Equality depends, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-even</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-equal.</hi> An hundred pounds in the exchange of any Commodity, are preciſely worth but an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105386:18"/>pounds. But to the Uſurer, an hundred pounds are of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of an hundred and ſix, or more, according to his own pleaſure (for his <hi>Will</hi> muſt be the <hi>Standard</hi> of <hi>Worth, Price,</hi> and <hi>Value</hi>) and to the Debtor or Borrower, they avayle but ninety four pounds or under. I would fain ſee the Commutative Juſtice of this, which according to all, conſiſts in an <hi>Arithmetical</hi> exact <hi>proportion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here again they have recourſe to their former refuge; The Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer forſooth, only recompenſes the loſs of a <hi>poſſible gain</hi> he might have purchaſed; and he takes the Intereſt as a <hi>Reward</hi> of that <hi>poſſible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> the Borrower is preſum'd to have made with his Money. But I anſwer for once and all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is no ſufficient Proportion between an Actual, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible gaine, and a meer poſſible one, attended by a multitude of Caſualites; this is apparent in other bargains. For example, why may not a Horſe-courſer ſell a Horſe with a ſafe Conſcience for five times as much as he knows him to be worth, becauſe there is a <hi>poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of the Buyers being ſet upon by Robbers, and for-ought he knows the Horſe being very fleet, may ſave both his life and 200 pieces he has about him? The like may be inſtanced in an hundred o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions. So that it is not the uncertain hopes of a future Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, but the preſent, real and intrinſecal value of the thing, that muſt ſway in ſetting the rate and price of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whoſoever will adjoyn ſuch Cautions as theſe, in his Lending, namely, to receive an equitable part (according to the Eſtimate of prudent, honeſt, and indifferent Judges) of the In-comes from the Principal, when they are actually in Being, and in the Borrowers hand; and withal, be willing to venture a competent ſhare of his own Principal, ſhould it happen to miſcarry; I have nothing to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue againſt his contract, but conclude it warrantable. However, to think that our Money-Merchants now a-days act upon ſuch ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous principles in their dealings,—<hi>Credat Indaus Apella,</hi>—it is beyond my Faith, and I am ſure out of the common roade both of their Law and practice.</p>
               <p>That I have not been over rigid in cenſuring, I might eaſily evince from the writings of Authors of the higheſt Ranck and undoubted Authority, who unanimouſly condemn far ſmaller matters than I have here impeached. I will but give you a taſte of ſome few. The The Learned Cardinal <hi>Tolet</hi> ſayes, It is Uſury, though I have but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105386:18"/>an intention, without expreſſing it in the contract of receiving more than I gave forth, as due upon the ſcore of Lending. Cardinal <hi>Lugo</hi> calls it Uſury to Lend Money, that I may obtain ſome Office or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment under him to whom I Lend. To Lend old Corn, with ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligation of repaying new, if I foreſee the new will be better and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, is Uſury, as <hi>Sylveſter</hi> and <hi>Navarre</hi> teach. It is Uſury to lend and lay a Juridical Obligation on the Borrower, either to lend to thee again, or to buy in thy ſhop, or to ſerve under thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Leſſius, Layman,</hi> and <hi>Bonacina</hi> affirm. It is Uſury, as <hi>Salas</hi> very well proves, to lend to the Prince or Common-wealth, that thou mayſt be free from Tribute and Taxes. It is Uſury to oblige the Borrower to accept part of the Money in <hi>thy</hi> Wares and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, in the judgment of that great Caſuiſt <hi>Diana.</hi> To lend Money on this Condition, that the Borrower at his great coſt and charges procure it from one of my Debtors, of whom I could not have got it without much difficulty and trouble, is Uſury, if we believe the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Merchantius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To go a little higher. In the Provincial Synods of <hi>Cambray,</hi> Anno 1586. <hi>Mechline</hi> 1570. St. <hi>Omers,</hi> 1583. <hi>Ipres.</hi> 1577. In a ſpecial Edict ſet forth by <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> it was peremptorily decreed, that <hi>No Tutor or Guardian of Orphans, under pretence of increaſing their Patrimony, ſhould let out their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from year to year for a certain gain above the Capital, reſerving a faculty or power of calling in the Principal or Capital ſum, either when the Pupils came to age, the day of Marriage, or otherwiſe at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> The aforeſaid Authority calls all ſuch Contracts Uſury, and proceeds againſt ſuch Lenders, as Uſurers, and declares the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract or Obligation <hi>invalid</hi> or of no force.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Provincial Synods,</hi> let us aſcend to <hi>General Councils.</hi> The Council of <hi>Agatha</hi> before cited, poſitively defines Uſury to be the receiving of <hi>more</hi> than was lent, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. The firſt <hi>Nicene</hi> Council declares it a mortal or heinous ſin, and puniſhes it in the Clergy with Degradation, <hi>Can.</hi> 17. The firſt Council of <hi>Arles</hi> forbids Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers the Participation of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> The ſecond ratifies the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the firſt, <hi>chap.</hi> 14. The firſt Council of Carthage uſes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles word, and terms it <hi>Turpe Lucrum,</hi> filthy gain, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. The <hi>Eliberitan</hi> Council formally degrades the Clergy, and Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the Laity that are Guilty, <hi>cap.</hi> 20. and the Council of <hi>Toures</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105386:19"/>ſeverely prohibits it, <hi>chap.</hi> 13. But the moſt terrible of all is the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council under <hi>Alexander</hi> the III. <hi>chap.</hi> 25. It is too long to tranſcribe, but it confirms the cenſures that went before, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-adds others.</p>
               <p>As to the matter of Law, I fear the Uſurer will find but little fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Canon Law both finds him guilty, and condemns him. The fifth book of <hi>Decretals,</hi> the 47th. diſtinction in the Decrees, <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. &amp; 4. wholly conſound him. Two Decretal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, one of Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> the other of Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt him; by vertue of which, while he is well in health, he muſt not receive the Euchariſt in the Church, nor make any Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; when he is ſick, he is not ſo much as to be viſited, or permitted to make his Will; nor when dead, is he admitted to Chriſtian Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. Nay, which I wiſh would be laid well to heart, the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors who perſwade, the Procurers, the Publick Notaries and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, who aſſiſt at, the Lawyers who defend, the Judges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates who countenance ſuch Contracts, the Confeſſors who abſolve him, are all involved in the ſame crime, and ſubjected to the ſame <hi>Anathema.</hi> The Authentick Records of Primitive times aſſure us, that the perſon who was but ſuſpected of Uſury, was neither vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed the Kiſs of Peace in the Church, nor reſpected with common ſalutation in the ſtreets; his houſe was generally called the Seat of Satan, nor was it lawful for any Chriſtian to ſetch fire from thence.</p>
               <p>Nor doth the Civil Law handle him more civilly. <hi>Cato</hi> a Heathen in his Treatiſe <hi>de Re Ruſtica,</hi> ſpeaking of the Law of 12 Tables, ſayes thus, <hi>Our Anceſtor's both thought ſo, and put it among their Laws, that a Thief ſhould be condemned in double, but an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer in four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Reſtitution.</hi> So much harſher an Opinion had they of an Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer than of a Thief.</p>
               <p>It appears by the writings of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who flouriſhed, <hi>Anno</hi> 420. that in his time Uſurers were <hi>Infamous</hi> by Law, and eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unworthy to be admitted to any publick Office in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>As to the Principles of the Civil Law, they directly thwart the Uſurers practice, as will be manifeſt by a brief Recapitulation of ſome of them. I find them reckon'd up ready to my hand by <hi>Hotto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105386:19"/>a Grave and Judicious Conſcientious Authour, as he is cited by Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> in his Theological Determination of this point. They are theſe following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. It is of the very Eſſence and Nature of Lending, that it be free and gratuitous.</item>
                  <item>2. We are not to receive moſt certain profit from very uncertain Negotiation or Adventures.</item>
                  <item>3. Where Nothing is Exchanged, Nothing of Gain is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted.</item>
                  <item>4. Society cannot ſubſiſt without a Communication of Profits and Damages, or Hazards.</item>
                  <item>5. Things that are conſumed <hi>by</hi> or <hi>in</hi> their very Uſing, neither in natural nor civil Reaſon are capable of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus fructus,</hi> which is the Uſe or profit of what is another's, the propriety or ſubſtance of the thing being ſtill the Owners.</item>
                  <item>6. We are not to make advantage or profit of another mans Goods, the Owner being unwilling, or not yeilding plenary aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: As here the Borrower doth not, but is forced to undergoe ſuch and ſuch Conditions, or go without the Money his affairs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</item>
                  <item>7. The Law of an Inferiour cannot abrogate, or prejudice that of a Superiour; and therefore Humane Laws tolerating, or rather <hi>Regulating</hi> the exceſs of Uſury, can no ways invalidate or leſſen the Authority Divine, abſolutely forbidding it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are ſome few of thoſe many civil Axioms, which utterly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the Uſurers profeſſion and pretenſions.</p>
               <p>Now for our own Native Municipal Laws, I refer the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Statute-Books, with the other Elaborate Writings of the moſt Famous among thoſe of the Long Robe; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> in his Reports; where I preſume little will be found to the Uſurer's ſatisfaction. In ſhort, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is out of my Sphere, as I find it ſet down by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Under the <hi>Britons,</hi> it was provided by an Antient Statute, as we may ſee in <hi>Gildas,</hi> that it ſhould not be judged any Cheat to deceive an Uſurer.</item>
                  <item>2. Under the Saxons, by the 37th. Law of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, All Uſury was forfeited to the Crown.</item>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105386:20"/>
                  <item>3. Under the <hi>Normans</hi> in the Fourth of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, there was an Act againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> upon this very ſcore, and they were Baniſhed throughout the whole Kingdome: And from that time forward the Canon Law was in full force till the Fifth year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; which, how it was affected towards Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, may be more than gueſſed at, by what was ſaid a little before.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I have little to ſay as to the political part, being ſo ſeldome converſant either with diſcourſes of that Nature, or perſons of that Employment. However let me give you, though not the words, yet the ſence of one who was excellently well vers'd in both; by which you will ſoon diſcerne how incommodious, and well nigh inconſiſtent Uſury is with the Civil Government and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of a Nation.</p>
               <p>To omit the frequent feuds, quarrels, and diſcords, <hi>ſay's my Authour,</hi> that principally ariſe from this kinde of Exaction, and thoſe not alwayes to be decided by <hi>Gown-men,</hi> but ſometimes having recourſe to the <hi>Sword</hi> it ſelf, as appears by the Roman Hiſtory, where it is obſerved, how that firſt Revolt of the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beians</hi> or Commons, from the <hi>Senatours</hi> or Gentlemen, ſprung from the Uſurary proceedings of the latter with the former: To omit likewiſe thoſe continual murmurs, grudgings, repine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Curſes that accompany it, to the perfect alienating of Subjects mindes and Affections from one another, whence moſt of the Revolutions of Kingdomes are derived; it being impoſſible, in our Saviours reckoning, that a <hi>Community divided againſt it ſelf, ſhould be of long continuance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I may thus Reaſon;</p>
               <p>Money put out to Uſe, is either placed with a Poor man, or a Rich. If with a Rich man, uſually he either turns <hi>Monopoliſt,</hi> and ingroſſes a Commodity to himſelf; or <hi>Protopoliſt,</hi> fore-ſtalling the Markets; and afterwards by this means he inhances the Rates of Merchandize at pleaſure, converting that to the private <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering,</hi> and ſuperfluous ſwelling of one particular Member, which Reaſon deſignes for the common nouriſhment of the whole <hi>Body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique.</hi> And this, though it may be diſſembled for a time, yet muſt neceſſarily breed bad blood in the Republick.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105386:20"/>
               <p>If a perſon of a ſlender Fortune, light upon a good round ſumme by borrowing; it often happens that at ſuch an un-uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſight, he begins to foſter extravagant hopes, attempts too high matters, turnes Prodigal, and then Bankrupt; and after that, ſeeing his Fortune deſperate, his inclinations ſwim with it; let any <hi>Faction</hi> appear, let any <hi>Standard</hi> be Erected, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>David the Soveraign,</hi> or of <hi>Abſolam the Rebel,</hi> it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not, thither he Poſts, knowing it to be good Fiſhing in troubled Waters: Nor can hardly one among a thouſand Bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts be inſtanced in, who was not reduced to ſuch exigencies firſt by tampering with the Uſurer.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author leaves it to the conſideration of States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whether it be for the publique good to permit any to ſerape together, and hoard up Wealth by ſuch idle, lazie means; ſince all Mechanical Arts, Adventuring in Merchandiſe, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Manufactures, both in Town and Country (which are the very ſinews of a Common-wealth) will quickly come to nothing. For who is ſo ſottiſh as to run hazards, toyle night and day, compaſs Sea and Land for uncertain hopes, when he may, lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home, without the ſweat of his Browes, or the trouble of his Brayns, at his leaſure <hi>Increaſe</hi> and <hi>Multiply</hi> by that <hi>caſie Trade of Lending?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There remains nothing now but to view the Judgment of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, the Primitive and more purer Ages of Chriſtianity, and that both in the Greek and Latine Fathers; whereby we ſhall diſcover the minde of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Church.</p>
               <p>This hath been done in, part, ſcatteringly here and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and therefore it will be ſufficient ſummarily to ſupply the teſt.</p>
               <p>And, firſt occurrs that moſt antient Writer <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi> lib. Stromat. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>It is not the part of a Righteous Man to put out his Money to Uſe; but with a liberal hand and minde to contribute to the Neceſſitous.</p>
               </q>
               <p>St. <hi>Baſil</hi> upon the 15th. <hi>Pſalm</hi> (in his account the 14.) ſpends a whole Homily in Inveighing againſt Uſury.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> in an Epiſtle to a certain Biſhop, aſſures him that both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury and Increaſe are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105386:21"/>forbid in Holy Scripture, though under the pretenſe of a Contract or Bargain.</hi> By thoſe two words, he means <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> and <hi>Overplus,</hi> or <hi>Acceſſorium ſorti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> in his ſpeech to the Silent Father, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <q>Uſury and Increaſe have corrupted the Earth, while it gathers where it never Sow'd, and Reaps, where it ſcattered not;</q> nor doth it Till and improve the ground, but the wants of the Poor.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> is a moſt Rigid Taxour of it. In the end of his Fifty-ſeaventh Homily upon St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, he ſpares not the Laws themſelves that connive at it. In his Forty-one Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily on <hi>Geneſis,</hi> he diſcourſes thus, <hi>From the Beginning God forbad the</hi> Jews <hi>to take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What excuſe then can they have, who are more inhumane than the</hi> Jews? <hi>and after the Law of Grace, and ſo great mercy live inferiour to thoſe, who were under the Law of</hi> Moſes?</p>
               <p>The ſame Holy Father (or rather the Learned Authour of the <hi>Imperfect Work</hi> upon St. <hi>Matthew</hi>) in his Twelfth Homily ſpeaks to this purpoſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Chriſt commands us to Lend our Money, yet not with Uſury For he that puts his Money out to Uſe, at firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance indeed, he ſeems to give that which is his own; whereas in truth he gives not what is his own, but takes away what is anothers.</p>
                  <p>The Money of an Uſurer is like the biteing of an Aſpick (a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain venemous Creature.)</p>
                  <p>He who is Stung by an Aſpick, with great delight falls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and in that pleaſant Dream, dyes; becauſe then the Poyſon ſecretly over-ſpreads all his Members. So he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Money, and muſt pay the Uſe; for a while, he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies it a Courteſie; but at laſt the Uſe and Intereſt ſeizes on all his Eſtate, and turns the whole into Debt.—</p>
                  <p>If we were but contente with neceſſaries, that worſt ſort of men, Uſurers had never been heard of.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This for the Eaſtern Church, to which the Latine Fathers unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſubſcribe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>contra Marcion.</hi> 
                  <q>Peruſe the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> concerning the juſt man.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105386:21"/>
               <q>
                  <p>He hath not given his Money to Uſury, nor will accept of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verplus, which is Uſury.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Therefore firſt the Prophet would root out the profit of <q>Uſury, that he might the more eaſily accuſtome men patiently to looſe even the Principal it ſelf, if need were, ſince by the Law they were commanded to looſe the Intereſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Elegant Lanctantius, lib. 4. de Vero Cultu. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <q>If he have Lent any Money, he muſt not receive Uſe, that both the Courteſie may be compleat, and he keep his hands from other mens goods; For in ſuch kindes of Civility, every man muſt be contented with his own, nay, ſometimes not ſpare his own, that he may do good: But to receive <hi>more</hi> than he gave, is unjuſt; nor will a juſt man defile himſelf with ſuch Gain.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Fourteenth Chapter concerning <hi>Tobias;</hi> 
                  <q>What ever is above the Principal is Uſury.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>If it be lawful, why do you ſhun the Title? (as they do who call it Intereſt) and draw a veile over it, makeing Intereſt the Plaſter of Uſury? If it be unlawful, why do you ſeek for Increaſe?</p>
               </q>
               <p>What St. <hi>Jerom</hi> thinks of this buſineſs, you may ſee in the Title Page.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the Thirty-ſeaventh Pſalm. <q>Whatſoever it be, if thou expect to Receive <hi>more</hi> than thou Gaveſt, thou art an Uſurer and to be Condemned,</q> and forbids us to give Almes of the Money purchaſed by Uſury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the Great, in his Sixteenth Sermon concerning Faſting; <q>Whatever effect follows on Uſury, it is a Sin: So that the Uſurer muſt be either miſerable, by looſing what he gave; or more miſerable by obtaining what he gave not.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the Iniquity of Uſury is to be avoyded, <hi>quia fenus pecuniae, funus Animae,</hi> the Gain of the Money is the Loſs of the Soul.</p>
               <p>The Caſe of Orphans and other poor people is the greateſt difficulty in this matter. But we are in a point of Juſtice. In which <hi>Pauperis quoque non miſereberis in Judicio,</hi> Exod. 23.3. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a poor Man is not to be countenanced.</p>
               <p>He who made this Prohibition hath no where exempted them: and therefore to his Providence they muſt be referred, who hath
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105386:22"/>promiſed to have a ſpecial care over them, and be a Father, the Fatherleſs, and a Husband to the Widdow.</p>
               <p>In the interim, Merchants, and other pious diſpoſed perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> may undertake the management of their Stock, to their adva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, without entering into any ſuch formal Contract as we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> here diſputed againſt.</p>
               <p>Thus having Gratified your Requeſt in the Queſtio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> propoſed, I have no more to do, but Subſcribe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Madam ,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your most devoted Servant, <hi>T. S.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
